{"tossups": [{"question": "Former Nazi Klaus Barbie may have helped capture this leader of the ELN. This man captured an armored train after leading the winning side at the Battle of Santa Clara. This Argentinian wrote a memoir about his travels titled<em> The Motorcycle Diaries</em>. Alberto Korda\u2019s famous photo,<em> Guerrillero</em> <em>Heroico</em>, portrays this leader wearing a starred beret. For the point, name this international revolutionary who was executed in Bolivia in 1967, a central figure of the Cuban Revolution.", "answer": "Ernesto \u201c<b>Che</b>\u201d<b> Guevara</b> (accept pronunciations including a \u201cB\u201d sound or a \u201cV\u201d sound, accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Crates [CRAY-teez] of Mallus led one of these institutions in the city of Pergamum. Apollonius Rhodius and Eratosthenes led one of these institutions, which was supervised by Callimachus. Invading armies under \u2018Amr ibn al-\u2019As possibly burned that example of these institutions in Egypt. Ashurbanipal ordered the construction of one of these institutions in Nineveh, which held a copy of the<em> Epic of</em> <em>Gilgamesh</em>. Over 40,000 papyrus scrolls were housed in, for the point, what type of institution found in Alexandria?", "answer": "<b> Library</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man received funding for a machine patented in 1794 from Nathanael Greene\u2019s widow, Catharine Littlefield. This man supposedly assembled a musket in front of John Adams from a drawer of shuffled pieces he had manufactured. After observing a cat attempting to pull a chicken through a fence, this man created a product that allowed for easier separation of a certain crop\u2019s fibers and seeds. For the point, name this inventor of the cotton gin.", "answer": "Eli<b> Whitney</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These people defeated Syagrius to conquer the last rump state of the Western Roman Empire. The lands of these people in Western Europe were split into three kingdoms in the Treaty of Verdun in 843. These people came to Odo of Aquitaine\u2019s aid at the Battle of Tours, which stalled Umayyad expansion into Europe. For the point, who were these people, ruled from 481 to 751 by the Merovingians, who took most of Gaul from the Romans?", "answer": "<b> Frank</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The ministry of one leader with this surname was bribed by the arms company Bofors. Another leader with this surname ordered an attack on the Golden Temple in Operation Blue Star. One leader with this surname urged residents to buy homespun cloth instead of importing from the United Kingdom. This was the surname of Jawaharlal Nehru\u2019s daughter and grandson, who served as the third and sixth Prime Ministers of their country. For the point, give this surname of Mohandas, also known as The Mahatma, the nonviolent Father of Indian Independence.", "answer": "<b> Gandhi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This politician was derisively nicknamed The \u201cScreenmaster-General\u201d after he saved Lord Stanhope from punishment. A coalition known as the Country Party formed to oppose this politician, whose enemies Lord Bolingbroke and Robert Pulteney criticized him in<em> The Craftsman</em>. This man rose to power during his tenure as Chancellor of the Exchequer following the burst of the South Sea Bubble. For the point, name this man generally considered to be the first Prime Minister of England.", "answer": "Robert<b> Walpole</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This god was portrayed as an unknown jackal-like animal with a stiff tail. A golden disc formed on the head of this god after a trick involving laced lettuce. This god sometimes took the guise of a different deity by wearing a bird head while guarding the sun barge from Apep. After this husband of Nephthys cut his brother into 14 pieces, he fought Horus for the throne. For the point, name this Egyptian god of disorder and brother of Osiris.", "answer": "<b> Set</b> (accept<b> Seth</b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One work by this composer in D-flat major is meant to depict a dog chasing its own tail, and another work by him uses repeating eighth-notes to represent a storm. This composer wrote numerous \u00b4etudes, including the \u201cBlack Key\u201d and \u201cRevolutionary\u201d \u00b4etudes, and his Piano Sonata Number 2 in B-flat minor contains a well-known funeral march played at this composer\u2019s own funeral in 1849. For the point, name this composer of pieces such as the \u201cMinute Waltz,\u201d a Polish musician with a French name.", "answer": "Fr\u00b4ed\u00b4eric<b> Chopin</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler allied with Zimri-Lim of Mari, although he later reneged on that agreement and sacked the city. This ruler was succeeded by his son Samsu-iluna. This ruler turned on the king of Larsa after receiving insufficient military aid in his campaign against Elam. This Amorite king\u2019s best known document was perhaps the first to establish the presumption of innocence and called for \u201ceye for an eye\u201d punishments. For the point, name this Babylonian king with a famous \u201cLaw Code.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Hammurabi</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s first name means \u201clotus\u201d in Sanskrit. This woman prosecuted Ed Jew for nine felonies, including extortion and voter fraud, when she was the San Francisco District Attorney. This woman was the first Indian-American Attorney General of California, and became California\u2019s first Black Senator in 2016. For the point, name this woman, the first Black, female Vice Presidential candidate for a major U.S. political party.", "answer": "Kamala<b> Harris</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One civilization from this modern-day country used shicra-bags to reinforce structures at Caral. This country where the Norte Chico civilization lived was also where a ruler was captured after throwing Friar Valverde\u2019s Bible at Cajamarca. This country is the location of giant Nazca glyphs drawn in the desert sands. This country declared independence from Spain in 1821, and Jose de San Martin was named its first Protector. For the point, name this country where the Incas built Machu Picchu.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Peru</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Carl Armfeldt led a disastrous retreat of troops from this nation during the Carolean Death March. This nation\u2019s forces helped depose Augustus the Strong, installing Stanislaus I as king of Poland-Lithuania. A ruler of this nation was arrested by the Ottomans at Bender, where he had been forced to retreat after the Battle of Poltava. This country\u2019s \u201cAge of Liberty\u201d began after the death of its king Charles XII. For the point, what is this nation that lost the Great Northern War to Russia and once controlled much of what is today Latvia, Estonia, and Finland?", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Sweden</b> (accept<b> Swedish</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler defeated the Sherden sea pirates shortly after succeeding his father Seti I. In one event, this ruler supposedly fought off the chariots of Muwatalli II by himself. This ruler celebrated an unprecedented 13<em> sed</em> festivals during his reign. This pharaoh signed the first known peace treaty, which was negotiated with the Hittites sixteen years after he fought them at the Battle of Kadesh. For the point, name this longest-reigning pharaoh of Egypt.", "answer": "<b> Ramses II</b> (or<b> Ramesses II</b>, accept<b> Ramses the Great</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Legend has it that his 2000 funeral attendees were killed as to not reveal the location of his tomb. For the point, name this man, born Temujin, the founder of the Mongol Empire.", "answer": "<b> Genghis</b> Khan (pronunciation can begin with hard G, soft G, or CH; accept<b> Genghis </b>Huangdi; accept<b> Temujin</b> Borjigin before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A Roman expedition of this river turned back upon reaching the impenetrable expanse of the Sudd swamp. The Jonglei Canal scheme to increase the downstream flow of this river was effectively halted by a country\u2019s independence in 2011. The Battle of Omdurman was fought next to this river, while a different battle named for this river actually took place in Aboukir Bay. For the point, name this river, on whose banks the Valley of the Kings contains the tombs of the Pharaohs.", "answer": "<b> Nile</b> River (accept<b> White Nile</b> River before \u201cOmdurman\u201d)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The disadvantaged status of these people in one country is being addressed by a government program known as Closing the Gap, championed by swimmer Ian Thorpe. These people were the subject of youth seizures for over 80 years, predominantly in the Northern Territory, leading to the \u201cStolen Generation\u201d of these people. Stories of \u201cThe Dreaming,\u201d the faith followed by these people, include both the Rainbow Serpent and Captain Cook. For the point, name this indigenous people of Australia.", "answer": "<b> Aboriginal</b> Australians (accept<b> Aborigines</b>) Page 5", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A task arranged and originally led by this man was completed by Juan Sebastian Elcano in 1522. This man was incapable of completing the task as he was killed during the resistance of Lapu-Lapu at the Battle of Mactan. Things named for this man include a probe of Venus, a strait, and two irregular dwarf galaxies. For the point, name this Portuguese explorer who was killed in the Philippines and thus did not complete the first circumnavigation of the world.", "answer": "Ferdinand<b> Magellan</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s messy succession plan gave his empire to five different men, including Hannibalianus and Dalmatius. This emperor\u2019s ascension to power disrupted the Tetrarchy, which he ended with Licinius. This emperor defeated Maxentius at the Battle of the Milvian Bridge after supposedly seeing a vision of the Chi-Rho in the sky. This emperor\u2019s Edict of Milan granted benevolence to a certain religious group. For the point, name this first Christian emperor of Rome.", "answer": "<b> Constantine I</b> (accept<b> Constantine the Great</b>) Page 6", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}